Guide to the Countee Cullen Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Countee Cullen Collection
1923-1946
JWJ MSS 7
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.4
(4 boxes)
Countee Cullen gained fame principally as a poet, during the Harlem Renaissance, and later taught in the New York City school system.
Cullen, Countee, 1903-1946
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Countee Cullen Collection contains items presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection by various persons, including Mr. Cullen, by way of Carl Van Vechten, with one later purchase ("Karenge Ya Marenge").
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
COUNTEE CULLEN (1903-1946)
Recognized at an early age for his poetic gift, Cullen became one of the leading lights of the Harlem Renaissance. Following the success of his volumes of poems, he studied in France on a Guggenheim Fellowship, married Yolande DuBois, the daughter of W.E.B. DuBois, and taught in the New York City school system.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials relating to Countee Cullen.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Cullen, Countee, 1903-1946
- Correspondence, 1937-45, n.d.; Series I
  - Atkinson, Edward, 1937-45, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    Scope and Contents
    To: 0 / From: 51
  - Braithwaite, Fiona, 1926 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To: 1 / From: 0
  - Byrd, Sydonia, 1927 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cottingham, Clive, 1938-46, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    To: 0 / From: 5
  - DuBois, Yolande, 1923-29 (Box 1, Folder 9-15)
    To: 104 / From: 0
  - Grass, Bella, 1934 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gross, ---, 1945 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    carbon of letter from Cullen
  - Hughes, Langston, 1928 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jackman, Harold, 1923-45 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    To: 0 / From: 26 Includes letter from F.A. Cullen, notes from Jackman to Carl Van Vechten and notes by Carl Van Vechten
  - LaGuardia, Fiorello, 1945 May (Box 2, Folder 21)
    To: 1 / From: 1
  - Littleboy, Rex, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    To: 3 / From: 0
  - Sebree, Charles, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes letter from Harold Jackman to Sebree, letter from Owen [Dodson?] to Carl Van Vechten, and draft of poem, "Description of the Wakeupworld" by Cullen
    To: 0 / From: 12
  - Thomas, Rughmarie, 1925-26 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    To: 6 / From: 0
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1943 Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    To: 0 / From: 1
- Writings, Series II
  - The Black Christ
    - Holograph notebook with other poems, 1928-29 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Holograph notebook copy made for and inscribed to Clive Cottingham (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Excerpts, typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Copper Sun
    - Galley proofs, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Karenge Ya Marenge"
    - Holograph, signed, 1942 Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - The Lost Zoo
    - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Holograph copy inscribed to Roberta Bosley (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Typescript, corrected, inscribed to Roberta Bosley, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Introduction, "A Word About Christopher", typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "Second and final draft" (setting typescript), inscribed to Carl Van Vechten (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Includes photograph of Christopher Cat
    - Galley proofs, 1940 Sep 13 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Publicity statement, cover design and photo of Christopher Cat, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Medea ["Byword for Evil"]
    - Prologue and epilogue of Cullen's adaptation, holograph notebook (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Typscript carbon of script, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Epilogue, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - My Lives and How I Lost Them
    - Setting typescript, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 41-43)
  - One Way to Heaven
    - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44-45)
    - Setting typescript, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Includes: postcard from Harper and Brothers to Countee Cullen and from Harold [Jackman] to Carl Van Vechten
    - Play adaptation, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Poems
    - Drafts, titled and untitled, holograph and typescript, 1926-42 (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
      Includes: poems removed from letters to Edward Atkinson and letters to Carl Van Vechten
    - Holograph notebook, filled with French exercises and some poems (Box 4, Folder 50)